Does moringa live up to the hype?
Check out this video to find out.
"The Benefits and Side Effects
of Moringa Leaf Powder"
Moringa has been
called “the miracle tree,”
Moringa (Moringa oleifera)
is a plant commonly known
as the “miracle tree” due to
its purported healing powers
across a spectrum of diseases.
If “miracle” isn’t hyperbolic
enough for you, on the internet
it’s also known as “God’s Gift to Man”.
Is moringa a miracle or just a mirage?
“The enthusiasm for the
health beneﬁts of [moringa] is
in dire contrast with the
scarcity of strong experimental
and clinical evidence
supporting [the claims].
Fortunately, the chasm
is slowly being ﬁlled.”
There has been a surge in
scientiﬁc publications on moringa,
and in the last ten years the number
of articles is closer to a thousand.
What got my attention was
the presence of glucosinolates,
compounds that boost our
liver’s detoxifying enzymes.
I thought they were only
found in cruciferous vegetables
like cabbage, broccoli, kale,
collards, and cauliﬂower.
But no, it turns out they’re
also found in the moringa family,
with potency comparable to broccoli.
That’s exciting, but why
not just eat broccoli,
rather than mail-ordering
some exotic moringa powder?
Is there anything
special about moringa?
It’s “been described as the
most nutritious tree yet discovered”.
How much is that saying,
though? Who eats trees?
Supposedly moringa
“contains higher amounts of …
nutrients than most
conventional … sources”:
10 times the vitamin A of carrots,
12 times the vitamin C of oranges,
17 times more calcium than milk,
15 times more potassium than bananas,
25 times more iron than spinach,
and 9 times more protein than yogurt.
First of all, even if all this were true,
this is for 100 grams
of dry moringa leaf.
That’s like 14 tablespoons—
almost a whole cup of leaf powder.
Researchers have had trouble
getting people to even eat 20 grams,
and so anything more would
likely “result in excessively
unpleasant taste, due to the
bitterness of the leaves.”
And secondly, the nutritional
claims in these papers are
"adapted from Fuglie," which
evidently is just some lay publication.
If you go to the USDA nutrient
database, and enter a more
doable dose like the amount
you might get in a smoothie
(about one tablespoon for instance),
a serving of moringa powder
has as much vitamin A as
a quarter of one baby carrot,
and as much vitamin C as
one one-hundredth of an orange.
So, an orange has as much vitamin C
as a hundred tablespoons of moringa.
A serving of moringa powder
only has the calcium of
half a cup of milk, the potassium
of not fifteen bananas,
but a quarter of one banana, the
iron of a quarter cup of spinach,
and the protein of a third
of a container of yogurt.
So yeah, maybe nutritious,
but not off the charts
and certainly not
what’s commonly touted.
So again, why not eat broccoli?
It’s got the A-C-Calcium-potassium-
iron-and-protein of broccoli!
Moringa does seem to have
anticancer activity—in a petri dish—
against cell lines of breast cancer,
lung cancer, skin cancer,
and fibrosarcoma, while tending
to leave normal cells
relatively alone, but there
haven’t been any clinical studies.
What’s the point in finding
out that “[Moringa] … enhances
[the] sexual performance
[of] stressed rats.”
What are you supposed
to do with that?
Studies like this one, though,
started to make things
a little interesting.
Researchers were testing the effects
of a tablespoon of moringa leaf
powder once a day for three months
on antioxidant status and saw
a drop in oxidative stress,
as one might expect from
eating any healthy plant food.
But they also saw a drop in
fasting blood sugars from
prediabetic levels over
100 to more normal levels.
Now, that’s interesting.
Should we start recommending
a daily tablespoon of moringa
powder to diabetics?
Was it just a fluke?
Moringa and blood sugar control:
A review of the current evidence... next.
“Clearly, in spite of
the widely held “belief”
in the health beneﬁts of
[moringa], the interest of
the international biomedical community
in the medicinal potential
of this plant has been rather
tepid”—“spectacularly hesitant
[in fact,] in exploring its
nutritional and medicinal potential…
other “superfoods” such as garlic
and green tea have enjoyed
better reception,” but they also
have more scientific support.
There are thousands of human
studies on garlic and more than
ten thousand on green tea, but
only a few hundred on moringa.
The most promising appears
to be on the effects
of moringa on blood sugar control.
If you have people eat
about five cookies,
this is the kind of
blood sugar spike you get.
Add about two teaspoons
of moringa leaf powder
into the cookie batter, and even
with the same amount of sugar
and carbs, the blood
sugar surge is dampened.
Just having people
drink one or two cups
of moringa leaf tea
before a sugar challenge
“suppressed the elevation
in blood [sugar] in all cases
compared to [those who
drank plain water instead].”
Here’s the spike after
sugar with no moringa,
and here’s the reaction to
the same amount of sugar
30 minutes after
drinking moringa tea.
No wonder moringa is
used in traditional
medicine practice for diabetes.
But you don’t really know
if it can help until
you put it to the test.
Diabetics were given about
three-quarters of a teaspoon
of moringa leaf powder every
day for 12 weeks and got
significant improvements
in measures of inflammation
as well as long-term
blood sugar control.
But the reason they call it
a quasi-experimental study
is because there was no control group.
The researchers just took
measurements before and after,
and we know that just being
in a dietary study can lead
some people to consciously or
unconsciously eat more healthfully,
so we don’t know what
effect the moringa itself had.
Even in moringa studies
with a control group,
it’s not clear if the subjects
were randomly allocated.
And in this study, the
researchers didn’t specify
how much moringa
people were even given.
What does one tablet’s worth mean?
No significant improvement
in this study;
maybe they didn’t give enough?
This study used a tablespoon
a day and not only saw
a significant drop in
fasting blood sugars,
but a significant drop
in LDL cholesterol as well.
Two teaspoons a day didn’t
seem to help, so was it just
that a whole tablespoon is needed?
Apparently not, since finally,
a randomized placebo-controlled
study using a tablespoon of
moringa a day failed to show
any benefit on blood sugar
control in type 2 diabetics.
So, we’re left with a few
studies showing potential
but most failing to show benefit.
Why not just give moringa
a try to see for yourself?
That’s a legitimate course
of action in the face of
conflicting data when we’re
talking about safe, simple,
side effect free solutions.
But is moringa safe?
Probably not during pregnancy,
as about 80 percent
of “women folk” in some
areas of the world use it
to abort pregnancies, and its
effectiveness for that purpose
has been confirmed, at least in rats;
though breastfeeding women
may get about a half cup
boost in milk production
based on “six randomized,
placebo-controlled,
blinded, clinical trials”.
Just because moringa
has “long been used
in [folk medicine traditions]”
in no way proves
that the plant is safe to consume.
Lots of horribly toxic stuff,
like mercury and lead
for instance, have
been used in traditional
medical systems the world over.
But hey, at least “no major
harmful effects of [moringa] …
have been reported by
the scientiﬁc community”,
or more accurately, “no adverse
effects were reported
in any of the human studies that
[had] been conducted to date.”
In other words, no harmful effects
had been reported... until now.
“Stevens-Johnson syndrome …
following [moringa leaf] consumption”:
Stevens-Johnson syndrome is
probably the most dreaded drug
side effect, a rare but
potentially fatal condition
characterized by
“epidermal detachment.”
In other words, it can
make your skin fall off.
Fourteen hours after consuming
moringa, a guy broke out.
The same thing had happened
three months earlier,
the last time he had eaten
moringa, causing him to suffer
“extensive lesions with
blister formation
over [his] face, mouth, chest,
abdomen, and genitalia.”
“This case report
suggests that consumption
of Moringa leaf is better
avoided by individuals
who are at risk of
developing [Stevens-Johnson].”
Although it can happen to
anyone, HIV is a risk factor.
My take on moringa is that
the evidence of benefit
wasn’t compelling enough
to justify shopping online
for something special when
you can get healthy vegetables
in your local market like
broccoli which has yet
to be implicated in
any genital blistering.